[music]
Hey everyone, welcome to the L in space
podcast. This is Allesio, founder of
Colonel Labs, and I'm joined by Swix,
editor of L in Space.
>> Hello. Hello. We're here in the studio
with Jeff Dean, chief AI scientist at
Google. Welcome.
>> Thanks for having me. [laughter]
>> It's a bit surreal to have you in the
studio. I've I've watched so many of
your talks uh and obviously uh you your
career has been super legendary. So, uh
I mean, congrats. I I think the the
first thing must be said congrats on
owning the Purto Frontier. [laughter]
>> Thank you. Thank you. Parto Frontiers
are good and it's good to be out there.
>> Yeah. I mean I I think it's a
combination of both uh your you have to
own the Parto Frontier you have to have
like frontier capability but also
efficiency and then offer that range of
models [snorts] that people like to use.
uh and you know some part of this was
started because of your hardware work
some part of that is your model work and
uh you know I'm sure there's lots of
secret sauce that you guys uh have
worked on uh accumulatively but like
it's it's really impressive to see it
all come together in like this steadily
advancing frontier.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean I think as you say
it's not just one thing it's like a
whole bunch of things up and down the
stack
>> and uh you know all of those really
combined to help make you an OS able to
make highly capable large models as well
as you know software techniques to get
those large model capabilities into much
smaller lighter weight models that are
you know much more cost-effective and
lower latency but still you know quite
capable for their size. So
>> yeah,
>> how how much pressure do you have on
like having the lower bound of the prior
frontier too? I think like the new labs
are always trying to push the top
performance frontier because they need
to raise more money and all of that. And
you guys have billions of users and I
think initially when you work on the CPU
you were thinking about you know if
everybody that used Google we used the
voice model for like 3 minutes a day
they were like you need to double your
CPU number like what's that discussion
today at Google like how do you
prioritize frontier versus like we
actually need to deploy it if we build
it. Yeah, I mean I think we always want
to have models that are at the frontier
or pushing the frontier because I think
that's where you see what capabilities
now exist that didn't exist at the sort
of slightly less capable last year's
version or last [clears throat] six
months ago version.
>> Um at the same time, you know, we know
there those are going to be really
useful for a bunch of use cases, but
they're going to be uh a bit slower and
a bit more expensive than people might
like for a bunch of other broader use
cases. So I think what we want to do is
always have um kind of a highly capable
uh sort of uh affordable model that
enables a whole bunch of you know lower
latency use cases. People can use them
for agentic coding much more readily. Um
and then have the the high-end you know
frontier model that is really useful for
um you know deep reasoning you know
solving really complicated math problems
those kinds of things. And and it's not
that one or the other is useful. They're
both useful. So I think we like to do
both. And also, you know, through
distillation, which is a key technique
for making the smaller models more
capable, you know, you have to have the
frontier model in order to then distill
it into your your smaller model. So it's
not like an either or choice. You sort
of need that in order to actually get a
highly capable more modest size model.
>> Yeah. And I mean you and Jeffrey In came
out with this solution in 2014.
>> Don't forget L'Oreal Vine as well.
a long time ago. Like
>> I'm curious how you [snorts] think about
the cycle of these ideas even like you
know sparse models and uh you know how
do you re-evaluate them? How do you
think about in the next generational
model what is worth revisiting like a
yeah they're just kind of like a you
know you worked on so many ideas that
end up being influential but like in the
moment they might not feel that way
necessarily. Yeah, I mean I I think
distillation was originally motivated
because we were seeing that we had a
very large image data set at the time,
you know, 300 million images that we
could train on with, you know, I forget
like 20,000 categories or something, so
much bigger than ImageNet. And we were
seeing that if you create specialists
for different subsets of those image
categories, you know, this one's going
to be really good at sort of mammals and
this one's going to be really good at
sort of indoor room scenes or whatever.
and you can cluster those categories and
train on an enriched stream of data
after you do pre-training on on a much
broader set of images. You get much
better performance if you then treat
that whole set of maybe 50 models you've
trained as a large ensemble. Um but
that's not a very practical thing to
serve,
>> right? So distillation really came about
from the idea of okay what if we want to
actually serve that and train all these
independent sort of expert models um and
then squish it into something that
actually fits in a form factor that you
can actually serve. And that's you know
not that different from what we're doing
today. You know often today we're
instead of having an ensemble of 50
models we're having a much larger scale
model that we then distill into a much
smaller scale model.
Yeah, a part of me also wonders if
distillation also has a story with the
RL um revolution. So what let me let me
maybe try to articulate what I mean by
that. uh which is you can uh RL
basically spikes models in a certain uh
part of the distribution and then you
have to sort of well you can spike
models but usually sometimes it might be
lossy in other areas and it's kind of
like an uneven technique but you can
probably distill it back uh and you can
uh I think that the sort of general um
dream is to be able to advance
capabilities without regressing on
anything else
>> and I think like that that whole
capability merging without loss. Uh uh I
feel like it's like you know some part
of that should be a distillation process
but I can't quite articulate it. I
haven't seen much papers about it.
>> Yeah. I mean I I tend to think of one of
the key advantages of distillation is
that you can have a much smaller model
and you can have a very large uh you
know training data set and you can get
utility out of making many passes over
that data set because you're now getting
the logits from the much larger model in
order to sort of
>> sort of coax the right behavior out of
the smaller model uh that you don't
wouldn't otherwise get with just the
hard labels and and so um you know I
think that's what we've observed is you
can get, you know, clo very close to
your largest model performance with
distillation approaches. And that that
seems to be, you know, a nice sweet spot
for a lot of people because it enables
us to kind of for multiple Gemini
generations now, we've been able to make
>> the sort of flash version of the next
generation
>> as good or even substantially better
than the previous generations pro. And I
think we're going to keep trying to do
that because that seems like a good uh
trend to follow.
>> Um dare I ask uh so it was it was the
original map was Flash Pro and Ultra.
>> Uh is ultra are you just sitting on
ultra and distilling from that? Is that
like the mother load? [laughter]
>> Uh I mean we have a lot of different
kinds of models. Some are internal ones
that are not necessarily meant to be
released or served. Some are you know
our pros scale model and we can distill
from that as well into our flash scale
model. So I think you know uh it's u
it's an important set of capabilities to
have and also inference time scaling can
also be a useful thing to improve the
capabilities of a model and
>> yeah cool yeah and obviously I think the
economy of flash is what led to the
total dominance I think the the latest
number is like 50 trillion uh tokens I I
don't know I mean obviously it's
changing every day
>> but uh you know by market share
>> hopefully hopefully up [laughter]
>> no I mean there's no I mean Just the
economics wise like uh because flash is
so economical like you can use it for
everything like it's in Gmail now it's
in YouTube like it's it's in everything
>> we're using it more in our search
products of various AI mode overviews.
>> Oh my god flash parts AI mode. Oh my
god. Yeah that's yeah I didn't even
think about that.
>> Um [laughter] I mean I think one of the
things that is uh quite nice about the
flash model is not only is it more
affordable it's also a lower latency.
And I think latency is actually a pretty
important characteristic for these
models because we're going to want
models to do much more complicated
things that are going to involve, you
know, generating many more tokens from
when you ask the model to do something
until it actually finishes what you ask
it to do because you're going to ask now
not just write me a for loop, but like
write me a a whole software package to
do X or Y or Z. And so having low
latency systems that can do that uh
seems really important. and flash is one
direction, one one way of doing that.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, obviously our hardware
platforms enable a bunch of interesting
aspects of our, you know, serving stack
as well like TPUs. Uh the interconnect
between chips on the TPUs, uh is
actually quite quite high performance
and quite amendable to for example long
context kind of attention operations.
You know, having sparse models with lots
of experts. These kinds of things really
really matter a lot in terms of how do
you make them servable at scale.
>> Yeah. Does it feel like there's some
breaking point for like the protoflash
distillation kind of like one generation
delayed? I I almost think about almost
like the capability asmtote in certain
tasks like the pro model today is as
saturated some sort of task. Mhm.
>> So next generation that same task will
be saturated at the flash price point
and I think for most of the things that
people use models for at some point the
flash model in two generation will be
able to do basically everything and how
do you make it economical to like keep
pushing the pro frontier when a lot of
the population will be okay with the
flash model? I'm curious how you think
about that.
>> I mean I think that's true if your
distribution of what people are asking
people the models to do is stationary,
right? But I think what often happens is
as the models become more capable,
people ask them to do more, right? So I
mean I think this happens in my own
usage like I used to try our models a
year ago for some sort of coding task
and it was okay at some simpler things
but wouldn't do work very well for more
complicated things. And since then we've
improved dramatically on the more on the
more complicated coding tasks and now
I'll ask it to do much more complicated
things. And I think that's true not just
of coding but of you know now you know
can you analyze all the you know
renewable energy uh deployments in the
world and give me a report on solar
panel deployment or whatever. That's a
very complicated you know more
complicated task than people would have
asked a year ago.
>> And so you are going to want more
capable models to push the frontier in
some sense of what people ask the models
to do. And that also then gives us
insight into okay where does the where
do things break down? How can we improve
the model in these these particular
areas uh in order to sort of um make the
next generation even better?
>> Yeah. Are there any benchmarks or like
test sets that you use internally?
Because it's almost like the same
benchmarks get reported every time and
it's like all right it's like 99 instead
of 97. Like how do you have to keep
pushing the team internally too to like
this is what we're building towards?
>> Yeah. I mean, I think benchmarks,
particularly external ones that are
publicly available, have their utility,
but they often kind of have a lifespan
of utility where they're introduced and
maybe they're quite hard for current
models. You know, I I like to think of
the best kinds of benchmarks are ones
where the initial scores are like 10 to
20 or 30% maybe, but not higher. And
then you can sort of work on improving
that capability for uh whatever it is
the benchmark is trying to assess and
get it up to like 80 90% whatever. I I
think once it hits kind of 95% or
something you get very diminishing
returns from really focusing on that
benchmark because it's sort of it's
either the case that you've now achieved
that capability [snorts] or there's also
the issue of leakage in public data or
very related kind of data being being in
your training data. Um, so we have a
bunch of held out internal benchmarks
that we really look at where we know
that wasn't represented in the training
data at all. There are capabilities that
we want the model to have um that it
doesn't have now and then we can work
on, you know, assessing, you know, how
do we make the model better at these
kinds of things? Is it we need different
kind of data to train on that's more
specialized for this particular kind of
task? Do we need um you know a bunch of
uh you know architectural improvements
or some sort of uh model capability
improvements? You know what would help
make that better?
>> Is there is there such an example that
you uh a benchmark inspired an
architectural improvement? like uh I'm
just kind of jumping on that because you
just
>> uh I mean I think some of the long
context capabilities of the of the
Gemini models that came I guess first in
1.5
>> really were about looking at okay we
want to have um
>> you know [clears throat]
>> immediately everyone jumped to like
completely green charts of like everyone
had I was like how did everyone crack
this at the same time like [laughter]
>> right yeah I mean I think um and once
you're set I mean as you say that needle
single needle in a haststack benchmark
is really saturated for at least context
lengths up to 128k or something. I think
most people
>> don't actually have you know much larger
than 128k these days or 256 or
something. Um you know we're trying to
push the frontier of 1 million or 2
million context language.
>> I think Google's still the leader 2
million.
>> Yep. which is good because I think there
are a lot of use cases where you know
putting a thousand pages of text or
putting you know multiple you know
hourlong videos in the context and then
actually being able to make use of that
is useful but the the single needle in a
haststack benchmark is sort of
saturated. Um so you really want more
complicated uh sort of multi- needle or
you know more realistic take all this
content and produce this kind of answer
from uh uh a long context that sort of
better assesses what it is people really
want to do with long context which is
not just you know can you tell me the
product number for this particular
thing.
>> Yeah it's retrieval it's it's retrieval
within machine learning. Uh yeah, it's
it's interesting because like I think
that the more meta lesson level I'm
trying to operate at here is uh you have
a benchmark you're like okay I see the
architectural thing I need to do in
order to go fix that but like should you
do it because sometimes you know that's
an inductive bias basically that you're
Jason we used to work at Google would
say like exactly the kind of thing like
yeah you're going to win short term
longer term I don't know if that's going
to scale you might have to undo that
[laughter]
>> I mean I I I like to sort of not focus
on exactly what solution one should
drive but what capability would you want
and I think we're very convinced that
you know long context is useful but it's
way too short today
>> right like I think what you would really
want is can I attend to the internet
while I answer my question right
[laughter]
>> but that's not going to be solved by
purely scaling the existing solutions
which are quadratic so a million tokens
kind of pushes
>> uh what you can do you're not going to
do that to a trillion tokens, let alone,
you know, a billion tokens, let alone a
trillion. Um, but I think if you could
give the illusion that you can attend to
trillions of tokens, that would be
amazing. You'd be find all kinds of uses
for that. You would have um attend to
the internet. you could attend to the
pixels of YouTube and the sort of deeper
representations that we can form for a
single video, but across many videos,
you know, uh on a personal Gemini level,
you could attend to all of your personal
state with your permission. So like your
emails, your photos, your
>> yeah,
>> your docs, your plane tickets you have.
Um I I think that would be really really
useful. And the question is, how do you
get algorithmic improvements and system
level improvements that get you to
something where you actually can attend
to trillions of tokens in some
meaningful way?
>> Yeah. But by the way, I think I I did
some math and if like if you spoke all
day every day for eight hours a day, um
you only generate a maximum of like 100k
tokens, which like very comfortably
fits, [laughter]
>> right? But if you then say okay I want
to be able to um understand everything
people are putting on video.
>> Exactly. Exactly. Well also I think that
the classic example is um you start
going beyond language into like proteins
and whatever else is extremely
information dense.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think one of the things
about Gemini's
multimodal aspects is we've always
wanted it to be multimodal from the
start. And so, you know, that sometimes
to people means
text and images and video sort of
humanlike and audio audio humanike
modalities. But I think it's also really
useful to have Gemini know about
nonhuman modalities. like LAR sensor
data from say Whimo vehicles or like
robots or you know various kinds of
health modalities, X-rays and MRIs and
imaging and genomics information. Um and
I think there's probably hundreds of
modalities of data where you'd like the
model to be able to at least be exposed
to the fact that this is an interesting
modality and has certain meaning in the
world. uh where even if you haven't
trained on all the LAR data or MRI data
you could have because maybe that's not
you know doesn't make sense in terms of
trade-offs of you know what you include
in your main pre-training data mix at
least including a little bit of it is
actually quite useful because it sort of
>> uh tempts the model that this is a
thing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Do do you believe I mean
since we're on this topic and something
I just get to ask you all the questions
I always wanted to ask which is
fantastic. uh like there are there some
king modalities like modalities that
supersede all the other modalities. So
the a simple example was vision um can
on a pixel level encode text and deepc
had this deepr paper that did that. Uh
vision has also been shown to maybe
incorporate audio because you can do
audio spectrograms and that's that's
also like a vision uh capable thing like
so so maybe vision is just the king
modality and like
>> yeah I mean [laughter] vision and motion
are quite important things right
>> motion uh
>> video as opposed to static images
>> because I mean there's a reason
evolution has evolved eyes like 23
independent ways because it's such a
useful capability for sensing the world
around you which is really what we want
these models to be able to do is
interpret the things we're seeing or the
things we're we're paying attention to
and then help us in uh using that
information to to do things.
>> Yeah, I I think motion uh you know I
still want to shout out I think Gemini
uh still the only native video
understanding model that is out there.
Uh so I use it for YouTube all the time.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean, it's actually I
think people kind of are not necessarily
aware of what the Gemini models can
actually do with video. Like, uh, I have
an example I've used in one of my talks.
>> It had like, uh, it was like a YouTube
highlight video of 18 memorable sports
moments across the last 20 years or
something. So, it has like Michael
Jordan hitting some jump shot at the end
of the finals and, you know, some soccer
uh, goals and things like that. And you
can literally just give it the video and
say, "Can you please make me a table of
what all these different events are,
what when the date is, when they
happened, and a short description of the
event." And so you get like now an 18
row table of that information extracted
from the video, which is, you know, not
something most people think of as like a
turn video into SQL like table.
>> Yeah. Has there been any discussion
inside of Google of like you mentioned
tending to the whole internet? Right.
Google it's almost built because the a
human cannot tend to the whole internet
and you need some sort of ranking to
find what you need.
>> Yep.
>> That ranking is like much different for
an LLM because you you can expect a
person to look at maybe the first five
six links in a Google search
>> versus for an LLM should you expect to
have 20 links that are highly relevant?
like how do you internally figure out
you know how do we build the AI mode
that is like maybe like much broader
>> search [clears throat] and span versus
like the more human one.
>> Yeah. I mean I think even pre- language
model based work you know our ranking
systems would be built to start with a
giant number of web pages in our index.
Many of them are not relevant. So you
identify a subset of them that are
relevant with very lightweight kinds of
methods. Now you're down to like 30,000
documents or something. And then you
have gradually refine that to apply more
and more sophisticated algorithms and
more and more sophisticated sort of
signals of various kinds in order to get
down to ultimately what you show which
is you know the final 10 results or you
know 10 results plus other kinds of
information. And I think an LLM based
system is not going to be that
dissimilar, right? you're going to tend
to trillions of tokens, but you're going
to want to identify, you know, what are
the 30,000ish documents that with the,
you know, uh, maybe
30 million interesting tokens and then
how do you go from that into what are
the 117 documents I really should be
paying attention to in order to carry
out the task that the user has asked me
to do. Um and I think you know you can
imag you can imagine systems where you
have
you know a lot of uh highly parallel
processing to identify those initial
30,000 candidates maybe with very
lightweight kinds of models. Um then you
have some system that sort of helps you
narrow down from 30,000 to the 117
uh with maybe a little bit more
sophisticated um model uh or set of
models. And then maybe the final model
is the thing that looks at 117 things.
That might be your most capable model.
So I think it has to it's going to be
some system like that that is really
enables you to give the illusion of
attending to trillions of tokens. Um
sort of the way Google search gives you
you know not the illusion but you are
searching the internet. Yeah.
>> But you're finding you know a very small
subset of things that are that are
relevant.
>> Yeah. I I often tell a lot of people uh
that are not steeped in like Google
search history that uh well you know
like BERT was like used like basically
immediately inside of Google search uh
and that improves results a lot right
like I I don't I don't have any numbers
off the top of my head but like I'm sure
you that's obviously the most important
numbers to to Google. Yeah, I mean I I
think going to an LLMbased
representation of text and words and so
on enables you to get out of the
explicit hard notion of of particular
words having to be on the page, but
really getting at the notion of this
topic of this page or this paragraph is
highly relevant to this query.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I don't think people
understand how much LMS have taken over
all these very high traffic system. very
high traffic. Yeah, like [laughter]
>> it's Google. Uh it's YouTube. Uh YouTube
has this like semantics uh ID thing
where there's like every token or every
uh item in the vocab is a YouTube video
or something that predicts the video
using a code book which is absurd to me
for YouTube size. And then most recently
Grock also for for XAI which is like
>> I mean I'll call out even before LLMs
were used extensively in search we put a
lot of emphasis on softening the notion
of what the user actually entered into
the query so that
>> do you have like a history of like
what's the
>> yeah I mean I actually gave a talk in uh
I guess uh web search and data mining
conference in 2009.
>> Okay. uh where we never actually
published any papers about the origins
of Google search uh sort of but we went
through sort of four or five or six
generations four or five or six
generations of uh redesigning of the
search and retrieval system uh from
about 1999 through 2004 or five and that
talk is really about that evolution and
one of the things that really happened
in 2001 was we were
sort of working to scale the system in
multiple dimensions. So one is we wanted
to make our index bigger so we could
retrieve from a larger index which
always helps your quality in general uh
because if you don't have the page in
your index you're going to not do well.
Um and then we also needed to scale our
capacity because we were our traffic was
growing quite extensively. Um and so we
had you know a sharded system where you
have more and more shards as the index
grows. you have like 30 shards and then
if you want to double the index size you
make 60 shards so that you can bound the
latency by which you respond for any
particular user query. Um and then as
traffic grows you add more and more
replicas of each of those. And so we
eventually did the math that realized
that in a data center where we had say
60 shards and um you know 20 copies of
each shard we now had 1,200 machines uh
with discs. and we did the math and
we're like, hey, one copy of that index
would actually fit in memory across,200
machines.
>> Mhm.
>> So in 2001 we introduced uh we put our
entire index in memory.
>> And what that enabled from a quality
perspective was amazing because before
you had to be really careful about, you
know, how many different terms you
looked at for a query because every one
of them would involve a disk seek on
every one of the 60 shards. And so you
as you make your index bigger, that
becomes even more inefficient.
But once you have the whole index in
memory, it's totally fine to have 50
terms you throw into the query from the
user's original three or four word query
because now you can add synonyms like
restaurant and restaurants and cafe and
uh beastro and all these things. And you
can suddenly start uh sort of really
uh getting at the meaning of the word as
opposed to the exact semantic form. the
user typed in. And that was, you know,
2001, very much preLLM, but really it
was about softening the the strict
definition of what the user typed in
order to get at the meaning.
>> What are like principles that you use to
like design the systems, especially when
you have I mean in 2001 the internet is
like doubling tripling every year in
size. It's not like a you know, and I
think today you kind of see that with
LLMs too where like every year the jumps
in size and like capabilities are just
so big. Are there just any you know
principles that you use to like think
about this?
>> Yeah, I mean I think uh you know first
whenever you're designing a system you
want to understand what are the sort of
design parameters that are going to be
most important in deciding that you know
so you know how many queries per second
do you need to handle? How big is the
index you need to handle? How much data
do you need to keep for every document
in the index?
How are you going to look at it when you
retrieve things? um what happens if
traffic were to double or triple you
know will that system work well and I
think a good design principle is you're
want to design a system so that the most
important characteristics could scale by
like factors of five or 10 but probably
not beyond that because
>> often what happens is if you design a
system for X and something suddenly
becomes 100X that would enable a very
different point in the design space that
would not make sense at X but all of a
sudden 100x makes total sense. So like
going from a disk spaced index to a
in-memory index makes a lot of sense
once you have enough traffic because now
you have enough replicas of the sort of
state on disk that those machines now
actually can hold uh you know a full
copy of the me uh index in memory.
>> Yeah.
>> And that all of a sudden enables a
completely different design that
wouldn't have been practical before.
>> Yeah. Um, so I'm I'm a big fan of
thinking through designs in your head,
just kind of playing with the design
space a little before you actually do a
lot of writing of code. But you know, as
you said, in the early days of Google,
we were you growing the index uh quite
extensively. We were growing the update
rate of the index. So the update rate
actually is the parameter that changed
the most surprisingly. So it used to be
once a month.
>> Yeah. And then we went to a system that
could update any particular page in like
sub one minute.
>> Okay. Yeah. Because this is a
competitive advantage, right?
>> Because all of a sudden news related
queries, you know, if you're if you've
got last month's news index, it's not
actually that useful for
>> a special beast. Was there any like you
could have split it onto a separate
system?
>> Well, we did we launched a Google News
product, but you also want news related
queries that people type into the main
index to also be
>> sort of updated. So,
>> yeah. Yeah. It's interesting. And then
you have to like classify whether the
page is you have to decide which pages
should be updated at what frequency.
>> Oh yeah, there's a whole like uh system
behind the scenes that's trying to
decide update rates and importance of
the pages. So even if the update rate
seems low, you might still want to rec
crawl important pages quite often
because
>> uh the likelihood they change might be
low but the value of having them updated
is high.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. uh what you know
this uh you know mention of latency and
and saving things to this reminds me of
one of your classics which I have to
bring up which is latency numbers every
programmer should know.
>> Uh
>> was there was there just a just general
story behind that did you just write it
down?
>> I mean this has like sort of eight or 10
different kinds of metrics that are like
how long does a cache miss take, how
long does branch miss predict take, how
long does a reference domain memory
take, how long does a distance take
these
>> how long does it take to send you know a
packet from the US to the Netherlands or
something. Um,
>> why Netherlands by the way or is it is
that because of Chrome?
>> Uh, we had a data center in [laughter]
>> um so I mean I think this gets to the
point of being able to do these back at
the envelope calculations. So these are
sort of the raw ingredients of those and
you can use them to say okay well if I
need to design a system to do image
search and thumbnailing or something of
the result page you know how might I do
that? I could premp compute the image
thumbnails. I could like try to
thumbnail them on the fly from the
larger images. What would that do? How
much dis bandwidth I need? How many disc
seeks would I do? Um and you can sort of
actually do thought experiments in you
know 30 seconds or a minute with the
sort of uh basic uh basic numbers at
your fingertips. Uh and then as you sort
of build software using higher level
libraries, you kind of want to develop
the same intuitions for how long does it
take to you know look up something in
this particular kind of hash table I use
or you know how long will it take me to
sort a million numbers or something.
>> Yeah. The the reason I bring it up
actually is actually for I think like
two years now I've been trying to make
numbers every AI programmer should know.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Uh I don't have a great one. uh because
it's not as it's not physical constants
like you have physical constants in here
you know it's and
>> uh but I do think like uh so a simple
one would be number of parameters to um
uh disk size if you if you need to
convert that uh which is a simple bite
conversion that's not that's nothing
interesting I wonder if you have any if
you want if you if you were to update
your
>> I mean I think uh it's really good to
think about uh calculations you're doing
in a model either for training or
inference. Um,
often a good way to view that is how
much uh state will you need to bring in
from memory either like onchip SRAMM or
HPM from the accelerator attached uh
memory or DRAM or over the network. Um
and then how expensive is that data
motion relative to uh the cost of say an
actual multiply in the matrix multiply
unit
>> and that cost is actually really really
low right because it's you know order
you know uh depending on your precision
I think it's like sub pico one picole
>> oh okay you measure it by energy
>> yeah yeah I mean it's all going to be
about energy and how do you make the
most energy efficient
Um, and then moving data from the SRAMM
on the other side of the chip, not not
even off the off chip, but on the other
side of the same chip can be, you know,
a thousand pajles.
>> Oh.
>> Or Yeah. And so all of a sudden this is
why your accelerators uh require
batching because if you move like say
the parameter of a model from SRAMM on
the on the chip into the multiplier unit
that's going to cost you a thousand pico
tools. So you better make use of that
that thing that you moved many many
times with. So that's where the batch
dimension comes in because all of a
sudden, you know, if you have a batch of
256 or something, that's not so bad. But
if you have a batch of one, that's
really not good.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Right. Because then you paid a thousand
podles in order to do your one pico
multiply.
>> I have never heard a energy based
analysis of batching. [laughter]
>> Yeah. I mean, that's why people batch,
right? Yeah, ideally you'd like to use
batch size one because the latency would
be great
>> but the energy cost and the the compute
cost inefficiency that you get um is is
quite large. So
>> yeah is there a similar trick like uh
like like you did with uh you know
putting everything in memory like you
know I think uh obviously Nvidia has
caused a lot of waves with uh betting
very hard on on SRAMM with grock. Uh I I
I wonder if like that's something that
you already saw with with the TPUs,
right? Like that that you had to uh to
serve at your scale. Uh you probably
sort of saw that coming like what what
what hardware uh innovations or insights
were formed because of what you're
seeing there.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think you know, TPUs
have this nice uh sort of regular
structure of 2D or 3D meshes with a
bunch of chips connected and each one of
those has HPM attached. Um I think for
serving some kinds of models,
>> uh you know, you you pay a lot higher
cost and time latency
um bringing things in from HBM than you
do bringing them in from uh SRAMM on the
chip. So if you have a small enough
model, you can actually do model
parallelism, spread it out over lots of
chips, and you actually get quite good
throughput improvements and latency
improvements from doing that. And so
you're now sort of striping your smalish
scale model over say 16 or 64 chips. Uh
but if if you do that and it all fits in
SRAMM, uh that can be a big win. So
yeah, that's not a surprise, but it is a
good technique.
>> Yeah. What about the TPU? design like
how much do you decide where the
improvements have to go? So like this is
like a good example of like is there a
way to bring the thousand pig jewel down
jewels [clears throat] down to 50 and
like is it worth designing a new chip to
do that? The extreme is like when people
say oh you should burn the model on the
ASIC and that's kind of like the most
extreme thing.
>> How much of it is it worth doing in
hardware when things change so quickly?
Like what what's the internal
discussion? Yeah, I mean we we have a
lot of interaction between say the TPU
chip design architecture team and the
sort of higher level modeling uh experts
because we really want to take advantage
of being able to co-design what should
future TPUs look like based on where we
think the sort of ML research puck is
going uh in some sense because uh you
know as a hardware designer for ML in
particular you're trying to design a
chip starting today and that design
might take two years before it even
lands in a data center and then it has
to sort of be a reasonable lifetime of
the chip to take you three, four or five
years. So you're trying to predict two
to six years out where what ML
computations will people want to run two
to six years out in a very fast changing
field. And so having people with
interesting ML research ideas of things
we think will start to work in that time
frame or will be more important in that
time frame. Uh really enables us to then
get you know interesting hardware
features put into you know TPU N plus2
where TPUn is what we have today.
>> Oh the cycle time is plus two
>> roughly. I mean
>> because uh
>> I mean sometimes you can squeeze some
changes into N plus1 but you know bigger
changes are going to require the chip
design be earlier in its lifetime design
process. Um, so whenever we can do that,
it's generally good. And sometimes you
can put in speculative features that
maybe won't cost you much chip area, but
if it works out, it would make
something, you know, 10 times as fast.
And if it doesn't work out, well, you
burned a little bit of tiny amount of
your chip area on that thing, but it's
not that big a deal. Uh, sometimes it's
a very big change and we want to be
pretty sure this is going to work out.
So we'll do like lots of careful ML
experimentation to show us uh this is
actually the the way we want to go.
>> Yeah.
>> Is there a reverse of like we already
committed to this chip design so we
cannot take the model architecture that
way because it doesn't quite fit?
>> Yeah. Yeah, I mean you you definitely
have things where you're going to adapt
what the model architecture looks like
so that they're efficient on the chips
that you're going to have for both
training and inference of that of that
uh generation of model. So I think it
kind of goes both ways. Um you know
sometimes you can take advantage of you
know lower precision things that are
coming in a future generation. So you
might train it at that lower precision
even if the current generation doesn't
quite uh do that.
>> Mhm. Yeah. How low can we go in
precision?
>> People are saying like turner is like
[laughter]
>> Yeah. I mean I'm a big fan of very low
precision because I think that gets that
saves you a tremendous amount of energy,
right? Because it's poujles per bit that
you're transferring and reducing the
number of bits is a really good way to
>> to reduce that. Um, you know, I think
people have gotten a lot of luck, uh,
mileage out of having very low bit
precision things, but then having
scaling vectors that apply to a whole
bunch of, uh, those those weights
>> scaling. Okay. Interesting. You so low
precision but scaled up weights.
>> Yeah.
>> Huh. Yeah. Never considered that.
Interesting. Uh while we're on this
topic, you know, I think there's a lot
of um uh just the concept of precision
at all is weird when we're sampling, you
know, uh we just at the end of this
we're going to have all these like chips
that all do like very good math and then
we're just going to throw a random
number generator at the start and
[laughter]
>> so I mean I there's a movement towards
energy based uh models and pro
processors. I'm just curious if you've
obviously you've thought about it but
like what's your commentary? Yeah, I
mean I think there's a bunch of
interesting trends. So energy based
models is one. You know, diffusion based
models which don't sort of sequentially
decode tokens is another.
>> Yes. Um, you know, speculative decoding
is a way that you can get sort of an
equivalent very small
>> draft
>> batch factor uh for like you predict
eight tokens out and that enables you to
sort of increase the effective batch
size of what you're doing by a factor of
eight even and then you maybe accept
five or six of those tokens. So you get
five a 5x improvement in the
amortization of moving weights uh into
the multipliers to do the prediction for
the the tokens. So these are all really
good techniques and I think it's really
good to look at them from the lens of uh
energy real energy not energy based
models um and and also latency and
throughput right if you look at things
from that lens that sort of guides you
to solutions that are going to be uh you
know better from uh you know being able
to serve larger models or you know
equivalent size models more cheaply and
with lower latency.
>> Yeah. Well, I think I think I um it's
appealing intellectually. Uh haven't
seen it like really hit the mainstream,
but um I do think that uh there's some
poetry in the sense that uh you know, we
don't have to do uh a lot of shenanigans
if like we fundamentally design it into
the hardware.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I think there's
still a there's also sort of the more
exotic things like analog based uh uh
computing substrates as opposed to
digital ones. Uh I'm, you know, I think
those are super interesting because they
can be potentially low power.
>> Uh but I think you often end up wanting
to interface that with digital systems
and you end up losing a lot of the power
advantages in the digital to analog and
analog to digital conversions you end up
doing
>> uh at the sort of boundaries and
periphery of that system. M
>> um I still think there's a tremendous
distance we can go from where we are
today in terms of energy efficiency with
sort of uh much better and specialized
hardware for the models we care about.
>> Yeah.
>> Um any other interesting research ideas
that you've seen or like maybe things
that you cannot pursue at Google that
you would be interested in seeing
researchers take a stab at? I guess you
have a lot of researchers. Yeah, we have
a lot of our our research portfolio is
[laughter] pretty broad. I would say um
I mean I think [snorts] uh in terms of
research directions, there's a whole
bunch of uh you know open problems and
how do you make these models reliable
and able to do much longer kind of uh
more complex tasks that have lots of
subtasks? How do you orchestrate you
know maybe one model that's using other
models as tools in order to sort of
build uh things that can accomplish uh
you know much more significant pieces of
work uh collectively than you would ask
a single model to do. Um so that's super
interesting. How do you get more
verifiable uh you know how do you get RL
to work for non-verifiable domains? I
think it's a pretty interesting open
problem because I think that would
broaden out the capabilities of the
models, the improvements that you're
seeing in both math and coding. Uh if we
could apply those to other less
verifiable domains because we've come up
with RL techniques that actually enable
us to do that uh effectively that would
that would really make the models
improve quite a lot. I think
>> I'm curious like when we had no brown on
the podcast, he said um they already
proved you can do it with deep research.
Mhm.
>> Um, you kind of have it with AI mode in
a way. It's not verifiable.
>> I'm curious if there's any thread that
you think is interesting there. Like
what is it? Both are like information
retrieval of JSON. So I wonder if it's
like the retrieval is like the
verifiable part that you can score or
what are like yeah how how would you
model that that problem?
Yeah, I mean I think there are ways of
having other models that can evaluate
the results of what a first model did.
Maybe in retrieving, can you have
another model that says, is this things
are these things you retrieved relevant
or can you rate these 2,00 things you
retrieved to assess which ones are the
50 most relevant or something. Um, I
think those kinds of techniques are
actually quite effective. Sometimes that
can even be the same model just prompted
differently to be a you know critic as
opposed to a uh actual retrieval system.
>> Yeah. Um, I do think like there there is
that that weird cliff where like it
feels like we've done the easy stuff and
then now it's but it always feels like
that like every year [clears throat]
it's like oh like we know you know and
the next part is super hard and nobody's
figured it out and
>> uh like exactly with this RLVR thing
where like everyone's talking about well
okay how do we do the next stage of the
non-verifiable stuff and everyone's like
I don't know you know judge [laughter]
>> I mean I feel like The nice thing about
this field is there's lots and lots of
smart people thinking about creative
solutions to some of the, you know,
problems that we all see. Uh because I
think everyone sort of sees that the
models, you know, are great at some
things and they fall down around the
edges of those things and and are not as
capable as we'd like in those areas. And
then coming up with good techniques and
trying those and seeing which ones
actually make a difference is sort of
what the whole research aspect of this
field is is pushing forward. And I think
that's why it's super interesting. You
know, if you think back two years ago,
we were struggling with GSM8K problems,
right? Like, you know, Fred has two
rabbits, he gets three more rabbits. How
many rabbits does he have?
>> That's a pretty far cry from the kinds
of mathematics that the models can.
>> And now you're doing
Yeah. And erosure language. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Pure language. So that is a
really really amazing jump in
capabilities in you know a year and a
half or something. And I think um
for other areas it'd be great if we
could make that kind of leap. Uh and you
know we don't exactly see how to do it
for some some areas but we do see it for
some other areas and we're going to work
hard on making that better.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Like YouTube thumbnail generation
that would be very helpful.
>> We need that. That would be AGI. we need
for as far as content creators go.
>> I guess I'm not a YouTube creator, so I
don't care that much about that problem,
but I guess uh many people do.
>> It Yeah, it doesn't it doesn't matter.
People do judge books by their covers as
it turns out.
>> Um just to draw a bit on the IMO gold.
Um I'm still not over the fact that a
year ago we had Alpha Proof and Alpha
Geometry and all those things and then
this year we were like screw that, we'll
just chuck it into Gemini. What's your
reflection? Like I think this this
question about like the merger of like
symbolic systems and like and and LLMs
uh was a very much core belief and then
somewhere along the line people just
said nope we'll just all do it in LLM.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think it makes a lot of
sense to me because, you know, humans
manipulate symbols, but we probably
don't have like a symbolic
representation in our heads,
>> right? We have some distributed
representation that is neural netlike in
some way of lots of different neurons
and activation patterns firing when we
see certain things and that enables us
to reason and plan and, you know, do
chains of thought and, you know, roll
them back. you know that that approach
for solving the problem doesn't seem
like it's going to work. I'm going to
try this one. And you know, in a lot of
ways, we're emulating what we
intuitively think uh is happening inside
real brains in neural netbased models.
So it never made sense to me to have
like completely separate
discrete uh symbolic things and then a
completely different way of of uh you
know thinking about those things.
>> Interesting. Yeah. Uh I mean it's maybe
seems obvious to you but it wasn't
obvious to me a year ago. [laughter]
>> Yeah. I mean I do think like that
>> IMO with you know translating to lean
and using lean and then the next year
and and also a specialized geometry
model and then this year switching to a
single unified model that is roughly the
production model with a little bit more
inference budget uh is actually you know
quite good because it shows you that the
capabilities of that general model yeah
have improved dramatically and and now
you don't need these specialized models.
This is actually sort of very similar to
the 2013 to6 era of machine learning,
right? Like it used to be people would
train separate models for lots of
different each different problem, right?
I have I want to recognize street signs
in something. So I train a street sign
recogn recognition model or I want to
you know decode speech recognition. I
have a speech model. Right? I think now
the era of unified models that do
everything is really upon us and the
question is how well do those models
generalize to new things they've never
been asked to do and they're getting
better and better
>> and you don't need domain experts like
one of my uh so I interviewed Eay who
was on who's on that team
>> uh and he was like yeah I I don't know
how they work I don't know where the IMO
competition was held I don't know the
rules of it I just train the models I'm
good at training [laughter] models
>> and it's kind of interesting thing that
like people with these this like
universal skill set of just like machine
learning you just give them data and
give them enough compute and they can
kind of tackle any task which is
>> yeah right [laughter] and
>> a bitter lesson I guess I don't know
>> yeah yeah I mean I think uh general
models uh will win out over specialized
ones in most cases
>> so I want to push there a bit I think
there's one hole here which is like uh
there's this concept of like uh maybe
capacity of a model like abstractly a
model can only contain [clears throat]
the number of bits that it has and uh
and so
you know god knows like Gemini Pro is
like one to 10 trillion parameters we
don't know but uh the Gemma models for
example right like a lot of people want
like the open source local models that
are like that that that and and uh they
have some knowledge which is not
necessary right like they can't know
everything like like you have the luxury
of you have the big model and big model
should be able to capable of everything
but like when when you're distilling and
you're going down to the small models,
you know, you're actually memorizing
things that are not useful
>> and so like how do we I guess do we want
to extract that? Can we can we divorce
knowledge from reasoning, you know?
>> Yeah. I mean, I think you do want the
model to be most effective at reasoning
if it can retrieve things, right?
having the model devote precious
parameter space to remember obscure
facts that could be looked up
>> is actually not the best use of that
parameter space right like you might
prefer something that is more generally
useful in more settings than this
obscure fact that it has um so I think
that's always a tension at the same time
you also don't want your model to be
kind of completely detached from you
know knowing stuff about the world right
like it's probably useful to know how
long the Golden Gate Bridge is just as a
general sense of like how long are
bridges, right? And uh it should have
that kind of knowledge. It maybe doesn't
need to know how long some teeny little
bridge in some other more obscure part
of the world is, but uh it does help it
to have a fair bit of world knowledge.
And the bigger your model is, the more
you can have. Uh but I do think
combining retrieval with sort of
reasoning and making the model really
good at doing multiple stages of
retrieval and reasoning through the
intermediate retrieval results is going
to be a a pretty effective way of making
the models seem much more capable
because if you think about say a
personal Gemini
>> Yeah. Right? Like we're not going to
train Gemini on my email. Probably we'd
rather have a single model that uh we
can then use and use being able to
retrieve from my email as a tool and
have the model reason about it and
retrieve from my photos or whatever. Uh
and then make use of that and have
multiple u you know stages of
interaction.
>> That makes sense. Do you think the
vertical models are like [clears throat]
an interesting pursuit? Like when people
are like, "Oh, we're building the best
healthcare LLM. We're building the best
law LLM." Are those kind of like
short-term stop caps or
>> No, I mean I think I think vertical
models are interesting like you want
them to start from a pretty good base
model, but then you can sort of I sort
of viewing them view them as enriching
the data distribution for that
particular vertical domain for
healthcare. say um we're probably not
going to train or for say robotics,
we're probably not going to train Gemini
on all possible robotics data. We you
could train it on because we wanted to
have a balanced set of capabilities. Um,
so we'll expose it to some robotics
data, but if you're trying to build a
really, really good robotics model,
you're going to want to start with that
and then train it on more robotics data
and then maybe that would hurt its
multilingual translation capability but
improve its robotics capabilities. And
we're always making these kind of uh,
you know, tradeoffs in the data mix that
we train the base Gemini models on. You
know, we'd love to include data from 200
more languages and as much data as we
have for those languages.
>> Yeah.
>> But that's going to displace some other
capabilities of the model.
>> It won't be as good at um you know,
Pearl programming. you know, it'll still
be good at Python programming because
we'll include enough of that, but
there's other longtail computer
languages or coding capabilities that it
may suffer on or multi- uh multimodal
reasoning capabilities may suffer
because we didn't get to expose it to as
much data there, but it's really good at
multilingual things. So, I I think some
combination of specialized models, maybe
more modular models. So it'd be nice to
have the capability to have those 200
languages plus this awesome robotics
model plus this awesome healthcare uh
module that all can be knitted together
to work in concert and called upon in
different circumstances, right? Like if
I have a health related thing, then it
should enable using this health module
in conjunction with the main base model
to be even better at those kinds of
things.
>> Yeah. Installable knowledge. Yeah.
Right. just [clears throat] download as
a as a
>> and some of that installable stuff can
come from retrieval,
>> but some of it probably should come from
training on you know uh 100 billion
tokens or a trillion tokens of health
data.
>> Yeah. And for listeners I think uh I
will highlight the GEMA 3 end paper
where they there was a little bit of
that I think.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I guess the question is like how
many billions of tokens do you need to
outpace the frontier model
>> improvements? You know, it's like if I
have to make this model better at
healthcare and the main Gemini model is
still improving,
>> do I need 50 billion tokens? Can I do it
with 100? If I need a trillion
healthcare tokens, it's like they're
probably not out there that you don't
have, you know, I think that's really
like the challenge.
>> Oh, I mean, I think healthcare is a
particularly challenging domain. So
there's a lot of healthcare data that
you know we don't have access to
appropriately but there's a lot of you
know uh healthcare organizations that
want to train models on their own data
that is not public healthcare data uh
not public health but public healthare
data. Um, so I think there are
opportunities there to say partner with
a large healthcare organization and
train models for their use that are
going to be, you know, more bespoke but
probably uh might be better than a
general model trained on say public
data.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I believe uh by the way al this
is like somewhat related to the language
conversation. Uh I think one of your
your favorite examples was you can put a
low resource language in the context and
it just learns [laughter] in context.
>> Oh yeah. I think the example we used was
Calamong which is truly low resource
because it's only spoken by I think 120
people in the world and there's no
written text.
>> So
>> so you can just do it that way just to
get in the context.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Yeah. But I put your whole data set in
context, right?
>> If you if you take a language like uh
you know Somali or something there is a
fair bit of Somali text in the world
that uh or Ethiopian Amharic or
something um you know we probably are
not putting all the data from those
languages into the Gemini based
training. We put some of it but if you
put more of it you'll improve the
capabilities of those models.
>> Yeah.
>> So or of those languages.
>> Uh yeah cool. Uh it's uh the I I have a
side interest in linguistics. I I I I
did a few classes in back in college and
like uh part of me like if I was a
linguist and I could have access to all
these models I would just be asking
really fundamental questions about
language itself like uh one is there's
one very obvious one which is superior
warf like how much does like the
language that you speak affect your
thinking but then also there are some
languages where there's just concepts
that are not represented in other
languages but some others many others
that are just duplicates right where uh
there's also another paper that people
love called the platonic representation
where you know like the the an image of
a cup is uh if you say learn a model on
that and you you you have a lot of text
with the word cup it eventually maps to
like roughly the same place in laten
space and so like that should apply to
languages except where it doesn't and
that's actually like very interesting
differences in what humanity has
discovered as concepts that maybe
English doesn't have.
[laughter]
>> I I don't know. That's just like my my
rant on languages.
>> Yeah, I I did some work on a early model
that fused together a languagebased
model with you have, you know, nice
word-based representations and then an
image model where you have trained it on
imageet like things. Yes.
>> And then you fuse together the top
layers of
>> uh no this is device
>> device.
>> Uh
the you do a little bit more training to
fuse together those representations. And
what you found was that if you give a
novel image that is not in any of the
categories in the image model it was
trained on the model can often assign
kind of the right c the right label to
that image. Um so for example um I think
uh telescope and uh binoculars were both
in the training uh categories for the
image model but um microscope was not.
M.
>> And so if you give it an image of a
microscope, it actually can come up with
something that's got the word microscope
as the label that are designed even
though it's never actually seen an image
labeled that.
>> Oh, that's nice.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, so yeah,
>> useful. Uh, cool. I think there there's
more general like broad questions, but
like I guess what what do you uh wish
you were asked more in in in general?
Like you know you have such a broad
scope. We've covered the hardware.
covered the the models research.
>> Yeah, I mean I think uh
one thing that's kind of interesting is
you know I I did a undergrad thesis on
neural network uh training uh parallel
neural network training uh back in 1990
when I got exposed to to neural nets and
I always felt kind of they were the
right abstraction but we just needed way
more compute than we had then. So like
the 32 processors in the department
parallel computer you know could get you
a a little bit more interesting uh model
but not not enough to solve real
problems. And so starting in 2008 or
nine, you know, the world started to
have enough computing power through
Moors law and, you know, larger
interesting data sets to train on to
actually, you know, start training
neural nets that could tackle real
problems that people cared about, speech
recognition, vision, and eventually
language. Um
and so um when I started working on
neural nets at Google in in late 2011 um
you know I really just felt like we
should scale up the size of neural
networks we can train using you know
large amounts of parallel computation
and so I actually revived some ideas for
my undergrad thesis where I'd done both
model parallel and data parallel uh
training and I compared them.
>> I called them something different. It
was like pattern partitioned and you
know model partitioned or something.
>> We'll have to Is it is it public? Can we
go dig?
>> Yeah, it's on it's on the web.
>> Okay.
>> Um but uh you know I think combining a
lot of those techniques and really just
trying to push on scaling things up over
the last you know 15 years has been you
know really important and that means you
know improvements in the hardware. So
you know pushing on building specialized
hardware like TPUs. Uh it also means you
know pushing on software abstraction
layers to let people express ML ideas uh
effectively. Um and then also working on
things like uh say sparse models. I've
felt for a long time that sort of
sparsely activated models are a really
important thing because you want the
models to have a lot of capacity to our
earlier discussion about remembering a
lot of stuff.
>> Yeah.
>> But you also want to be super efficient
in how you activate your models. So
you'd like you know trillions of
parameters but activate only you know
one 1% or 5% or 10% of that and um that
you know we did a early u paper on this
where we really scaled up uh you know
outrageously large neural networks that
the title I think that's Nome's uh
Gnome's wording in the title which is a
good catchy title.
>> I mean in 2017 he was out there talking
about one trillion parameter models.
>> Yeah. So I mean that that that is really
good because that gave you like a 10x
improvement in you know time to quality
or compute cost to qual a given quality
level relative to non-sparse models. Um
transformers similarly gave you a 10x to
100x improvement in you know uh compute
cost to a given quality level uh versus
say LSTMs at the time and all of those
things multiply together. Um so I think
all those things really are important to
work on you know the hardware the
systems infrastructure the you know
algorithmic aspects of model
architecture improving the data you know
improving the RL recipes all these
things uh are what are stacking together
and multiplying together
>> to give us models of 2026
are much more better than models of 25
and are awesomely better than 24 and 23
and
and and a huge uh honestly like
organizational challenge like there's
like a thousand people or maybe more
like I know I know when the first Gemini
paper came out it was like a thousand of
co-authors.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We have uh 10 pages of
co-authors in the in the tech [laughter]
report
>> but it was nice. I mean you know people
want to be acknowledged on probably a
historical paper.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think it's perfectly
good to have actually a lot of
co-authors and I do think
>> organizing that number of people so that
they're effectively pushing in common
directions that all all their work
actually sort of multiplies together in
the ultimate output which is you know
the next generation of model is actually
pretty tricky and we have awesome people
uh throughout the Gemini team to help
orchestrate this. So you know myself,
Noom and Oral are sort of helping steer
this and then we have people thinking
about you know what is the pre-training
uh setup look like what does the
infrastructure look like what does the
post-raining recipe look like and what
does the data preparation and eval
multimodal capabilities and IN
capabilities
>> um you know there's a lot of different
kinds of areas coding capabilities all
these areas are are super important and
it's really good to have people uh
paying close attention to those things
and then also paying close attention to
all the other things.
>> Yeah. I'm told Sergey is like very
actively back and like very much
involved in coding stuff.
>> Yep. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. We all use the
same micro kitchen.
>> Yeah. Uh oh. Okay. Like there's so many
jumping off point. Uh so by the way I
found out from the recent uh I mean
you've probably told this story a few
times but apparently Google brain was
also started in a micro kitchen.
>> Yeah. Yeah. [laughter]
>> Just like your micro kitchens are very
important.
>> Yeah. I don't know if people like
understand.
>> Yeah. Uh yeah, I actually bumped into
Andrew Ing who's a Stanford faculty
member and uh I knew him from I'd given
talks at Stanford a couple years before
so I sort of knew him and I'm like, "Oh,
what are you doing here?" He's like,
"Oh, I'm not sure yet. I just started,
you know, a couple weeks ago. I'm going
to spend one day a week here consulting.
Um I'm not sure what I'm working on, but
my students at Stanford are starting to
get good results um on using u neural
nets for speech uh recognition. I'm
like, "Oh, neural nets. I like neural
nets." Like I remembered back to my 1990
thesis. I'm like, "Oh, that sounds
interesting. We should train really
really big neural nets."
>> So [snorts] that was the
>> which you say that and that's a very
interesting first instinct, which is
that we should scale this up a lot.
>> Yeah. Well, I mean, I felt like
Google is is has lots of computational
uh capability and so if they were seeing
good results on, you know, what were
effectively single GPU or uh models,
>> you know, if we were uh we actually
didn't have GPUs in our data centers
then we didn't have any accelerators. We
had lots of CPUs, but you know, we could
build a software system that would
enable you to distribute with both model
parallelism and data parallelism across
lots of computers. And we ended up
training a pretty big model was 50x
bigger than any previous neural net as
far as we could tell. Um, so it's two
billion parameters uh vision model uh
trained on 16,000 CPU cores for like
multiple weeks. Uh and that's what gave
us really good it would gave us a 70%
relative error improvement in imageet
22k which is the 22,000 category thing
and that's how we really saw okay
scaling this up actually matters. We
didn't write a, you know, a
sophisticated scaling analysis, but we
had a a saying, bigger model, more data,
better results.
>> And that was our our mantra for like six
or seven years of scaling. And we every
time we did that, we saw better results
in speech, in language, in in vision.
>> Uh, speaking of um bets, and this might
and this, you know, I'll preface with
like this might be a little bit more
sensitive topic, but you have obviously
a lot of opinions about this. We had a
previous guest, David Juan, who used to
work for you, and uh he he kind of like
blames almost the brain marketplace as
like the reason that Google didn't
invest enough in language models. And I
wonder if that's uh something you would
you would agree with at the time or uh
is there like a different sort of
postmortm
>> the brain marketplace for computers
>> compute quotas where basically he was
like okay the like
>> David worked at OpenAI as VP engine then
he worked at Google he was like
fundamentally open was willing to go all
in like bet the farm on one thing
whereas Google was more democratic like
everyone had a
>> had a quota and I was like okay like
like if if you believe in scaling as an
important thing that's a that's an
important
organizationalwide decision to do.
>> Yeah. Uh yeah, I mean I think uh I would
somewhat agree with that. I mean I think
I actually wrote a one-page memo saying
we were being stupid by uh fragmenting
our resources.
>> Um so in particular at the time we had
uh you know uh efforts within Google
research on uh and and in the brain team
in particular on large language models.
We also had efforts on multimodal models
um in uh other parts of brain and and
Google research and then legacy deep
mind had uh efforts like um chinchilla
models and uh flamingo models. Uh and so
really we were fragmenting not only our
compute uh across those separate efforts
but also our best people and our best
ideas, right? And so I said this is just
stupid. Why don't we combine things and
have one effort to uh train
>> and this is the merge. Yeah.
>> To train an awesome single unified model
that is multimodal from the start that's
good at everything and that was the
origin of the Gemini effort and my one
page memo worked which is good.
>> Did you have the name because also for
those who don't know you named Gemini.
>> I did. Yeah. [laughter] Yeah. There was
there was another name proposed and I I
said, you know, it's sort of like these
two organizations
really are like uh twins
>> in some sense coming together. Um so I
kind of like that. And then there's also
the NASA interpretation of you know the
early Gemini project
>> uh being an important thing on your way
to um you know the Apollo project. So it
seemed like a good name. Twins coming
together,
>> right? Yeah. Nice. Um, I know we're
already running out of time, but I'm
curious how you use AI today to code.
So, I mean, you're probably one of the
most prolific engineers in the history
of computer science. Um, I was reading
on through the article about you and
Sanji's friendship and how you work
together [clears throat] and
>> you have one quote about you need to
find someone that you're going to pair
program with who's compatible with your
way of thinking so that the two of you
together are a complimentary force. Mhm.
>> And I was thinking about how you think
about coding agents in this like how do
you shape
>> a coding agents to be compatible with
your way of thinking like h how would
you rate the tools today? Like where
should things go?
>> Yeah. I mean first I think the coding
tools are you know getting vastly better
compared to where they were a year or
two two years ago. So now you can
actually rely on them to do more complex
things that you as a as a software
engineer want to accomplish and you can
sort of delegate you know pretty complex
things to these tools. And I think one
really nice aspect about the uh
interaction between a a human uh
software engineer and a a coding model
that they're working with is your way of
talking to that uh coding model actually
sort of uh dictates how it interacts
with you, right? Like you could ask it
please write a bunch of good tests for
this. You could ask it, please help me
brainstorm performance ideas. And your
way of doing that is going to shape how
the model responds, what kinds of
problems it tackles. You know, how much
do you want the model to go off and do
things that are larger and more
independent versus interact with it more
to make sure that you're shaping the
right kinds of of things? And I think
it's not the case that any one style is
the right thing for everything, right?
like some kinds of problems you actually
want uh maybe a more frequent
interaction style with the model and
other ones you're just like, "Yeah,
please just go write this cuz I I know I
need this thing. I can specify it well
enough." Um and go off and do it and
come back when you're done. And so I do
think there's going to be more of a
style of having lots of independent uh
software agents off doing things on your
behalf and figuring out the right sort
of human computer interaction model and
UI and so on for when should it
interrupt you and say hey I need a
little more guidance here or I've done
this thing now what now what should I
do? Um I think we we're not at the end
all answer to that question and as the
models get better that uh set of
decisions you put into how the
interaction should happen may may change
right like if you if you have a team of
50 interns how would you manage that if
they were people and I think it's not
>> do you want 50 interns [laughter]
>> you might if they're really good right
>> it's a lot of management
>> but but it's a lot of
Uh yeah, I mean I think that is probably
within the realm of possibilities that
lots of people could have 50 interns
>> and so how would you actually deal with
that as a person, right? Like you would
probably want them to form small sub
teams so you don't have to interact with
50 of them. You could interact with five
of five of those teams and they're off
doing things on your behalf.
But I don't know exactly what the how
this is going to unfold.
>> Yeah. How do you think about bringing
people like the pair programming is
always helpful to like get net new ideas
in the distribution so to speak? It
feels as we have more of these coding
agents write the code. It's hard to
bring other people into the problem. Say
you go to like you know you have 50
interns [clears throat] right and then
you want to go to nom shazir be like hey
nom I want to like pair on this thing
>> but now there's like this huge amount of
work that has been done in parallel that
you need to catch him up on
>> right
>> and I'm curious like if people are going
to be in a way more isolated in their
teams where it's like okay there's so
much context in these 50 interns that
it's just hard for me to like relay
everything back to you
>> maybe I mean on the other hand
like imagine a classical software or
organization without any AI assisted
tools, right? You would have, you know,
50 people doing stuff and their
interaction style is going to be
naturally very hierarchical because,
you know, these 50 people are going to
be working on this part of the system
and not interact that much with these
other people over here. But if you have,
you know, five people each managing 50
virtual agents, you know, they might be
able to actually have much higher
bandwidth communication among the five
people uh than you would have among five
people who are also trying to
coordinate, you know, a 50 person
software team each. Yeah. So,
>> how do you I'm curious how you change
your just working rhythm, you know, like
do you spend more time ahead with people
going through specs and design goals
like
>> um I mean I do think it's interesting
that you know whenever people were
taught how to write software they were
taught that it's really important to
write specifications super clearly. But
no one really believed that. Like it was
like yeah whatever I don't need to do
that I'm going to [laughter]
>> really
>> I don't know. I mean, writing the
English the English language
specification was never kind of an
artifact that was really paid a lot of
attention to. I mean, it was important,
but it wasn't sort of the thing that
drove the actual creative process quite
as much as if you
specify what software you want the agent
to write for you, you'd better be pretty
darn careful in how you specify that
because that's going to dictate the
quality of the output, right? like if
you if you don't cover that it needs to
handle this kind of thing or that this
is a super important corner case or that
you know you really care about the
performance of this part of it you know
it may uh not do what you want and the
better you get at interacting with these
models and and I think one of the ways
people will get better is they will get
really good at crisply specifying things
rather than leaving things to ambiguity
>> and that is actually probably not a bad
It's not a bad skill to have regardless
of whether you're a software engineer or
a you know trying to do some other kind
of uh task. You know, being able to
crisply specify what it is you want.
It's going to be really important.
>> Yeah. My joke is um you know, good
prompting [clears throat] is in uh
indistinguishable from sufficially
advanced executive communication. Like
it's like writing an internal memo. Like
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Weigh your words very carefully. And
also I think very important to be
multimodal, right? I think one thing
that anti-gravity from from Google also
did was like just come out the gate very
very strong multimodal including videos
and that's the highest bandwidth
communication prompt that you can give
the
>> the model which is fantastic.
>> Yeah.
>> How do you collect things that you often
you would have in your mind. So you have
this amazing like performance hints
thing that you wrote about how to look
for performance improvements and is
there a lot more value in like people
writing these like generic things down
so that they can then put them back as
like potential retrieval artifacts for
the model like or do I have like the
edge cases is like a good example right
it's like [snorts] if you're building
systems you already have in your mind
specific edge cases depending on it but
now you have to like every time repeat
it
>> like are you having people spend a lot
more I'm writing out more generic things
to bring back or
>> um I mean [snorts] I do think
[clears throat] well-written guides of
of how to do good software engineering
are going to be useful because they can
be used as input to models or you know
read by other developers so that their
prompts are you know more clear about
what the the underlying software system
should should be doing. Um, you know, I
think it may not be that you need to
create a custom one for every situation.
If you have general guides and put those
into, you know, the context of a coding
agent that that can be helpful like in
you can imagine one for distributed
systems. You could say, okay, think
about failures of these kinds of things
and these are some techniques you can
deal with failures. you know, you can
have uh, you know, Paxos like
replication or, you know, you can, uh,
send the request to two places and
tolerate failure because you only need
one of them to come back. You know, a
little description of 20 techniques like
that in building distributed systems
probably would go a long way to having a
coding agent be able to sort of cobble
up more reliable and robust distributed
systems.
>> Yeah. Yeah. [clears throat] Wonder when
Gemini will be able to build spanner,
>> right? Probably already has the code
inside, you know. [laughter]
>> Yeah, that I mean that's a good example,
right? When you have like you know the
cap theorem and it's like well this is
like truth and you cannot break that and
then you build something that broke it.
Like I'm curious like models in a way
are like [clears throat] what did he say
he broke it? Would you say you broke cat
theorem?
>> Really? Yeah. Okay. All right.
>> I mean [laughter]
>> under local assumptions. Yeah. And some
and they're like, you know, good clocks.
>> Yeah. [laughter] It's like some
sometimes you don't have to like always
follow what is known to be true. And I I
think models in a way like if you tell
them something, they like really buy
into that, you know. Um
>> so yeah, just more thinking than any
answer on how to fix that. Yeah, my my
uh you know just on this like like big
prompting and and uh iteration you know
I think that coming back to your latency
point um I always I always trying to one
one AB test or experiment or benchmark
or research I would like is what is the
uh performance difference between let's
say three dumb fast model calls with
human alignment because the human will
correct
>> human alignment means the human looks at
the first one and produces a new prompt
for the second one as opposed to like
you [clears throat] spec it out, you
know, you spend a long time writing a
pro a big big fat prompt and then you
have a very smart model do it, right?
You know, because uh really is is our
lacks in performance uh an issue of
like, well, you just haven't specified
well enough. There's no universe in
which I can produce what you want
because you just haven't told me,
>> right? It's underspecified. So, I could
produce 10 different things and only one
of them is the thing you wanted.
>> Yeah. And the multi-turn taking with a
flash model is enough.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Yeah. I'm I'm a big believer in pushing
on latency because I think being able to
have really low latency interactions
with a system you're using is just much
more delightful than something that is,
you know, 10 times as slow or 20 times
as slow. And I think, you know, in the
future, we'll see models that are and
and underlying software and hardware
systems that are 20x lower latency than
what we have today, 50x lower latency.
And that's going to be really really
important for systems that need to do a
lot of stuff uh between your
interactions.
>> Yeah. Yeah. There's two extremes, right?
And then meanwhile [clears throat] you
also have deep think which is all the
way on the other side,
>> right? [laughter] But you would use deep
think all the time if it weren't for
cost and latency, right? If if you could
have that capability in a model because
the latency improvement was 20x uh in
the underlying hardware and system and
costs, you know, there's no reason you
wouldn't want that.
>> Yeah.
But at the same time, then you'd
probably have a model that is even
better that would take you 20 times
longer even on that new hardware.
>> Yeah. Uh you know that there's the Fredo
curve keeps climbing. Um
>> yeah,
>> onward and outward. on way. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Should we ask him for predictions
to to go? I don't know if you have any
>> predictions that you that you like to
keep, you know, like uh one one way to
do this is you have your tests whenever
a a new model comes out that you run. Uh
what's something that you're not quite
happy with yet that you think will get
done soon?
>> Um
let me make two predictions that are not
quite in that vein.
>> Yeah. So I think a personalized model
that knows you and knows all your state
and is able to retrieve over all state
you have access to that you opt into is
going to be incredibly useful compared
to a more generic model that doesn't
have access to that. So like can
something attend to everything I've ever
seen, every email, every photo, every
video I've watched. That's going to be
really useful. uh I think uh more and
more specialized hardware is going to
enable much lower latency models and
much more capable models for affordable
prices uh than say the current current
status quo. Uh that's going to be also
quite important.
>> Yeah. When you say much lower latency,
uh people usually talk in tokens per
second. Is that a term that is okay?
Okay. Uh you know [clears throat] we're
at let's say 100 now. Yeah, we can go to
the thousands. Is it meaningful to go 10
thousands?
>> Yes.
>> Really? Okay.
>> Absolutely. Right.
>> Yeah. Because of chain of thought and
all
>> chain of thought reasoning. I mean you
could think you know uh many more
tokens. You could do many more parallel
rollouts. You could generate way more
code uh and check that the code is
correct with uh chain of thought
reasoning. So I think you know being
able to do that at 10,000 tokens per
second would be awesome.
>> Yeah. At 10,000 tokens per second you
are no longer reading code. Yeah. like
you'll just generate it. You'll not
remember it may not it may not
>> end up with 10,000 tokens of code
a thousand tokens of code that with
9,000 tokens of reasoning behind it.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Which would actually be probably much
better code to read.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. If I had more time, I would have
written a shorter letter.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um awesome, Jeff. This was amazing.
Thanks for making the time.
>> Thank you. It's been it's been fun.
Thanks for having me.
>> [music]